<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0"><channel><title><![CDATA[Moritz Hamann]]></title><description><![CDATA[Personal blog]]></description><link>http://moritzhamann.com</link><generator>RSS for Node</generator><lastBuildDate>Sun, 12 Jan 2025 08:58:09 GMT</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="http://moritzhamann.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title><![CDATA[New site - new ambitions]]></title><description><![CDATA[<p>Over the course of the last few weekends I finally took the time to revive this blog.
In the process I've scraped the old <a href="https://gohugo.io">Hugo</a> based site and redone it entirely in
<a href="https://metalsmith.io">metalsmith</a>.</p>
<p>This post tries to shed some background on the reasons (spoiler: personal preferences), how metalsmith
is set up for this page and what I'm planning to publish going forward.</p>
<h2 id="a-bit-of-history">A bit of history</h2>
<p>When I first registered this domain, it was mostly to reserve it for the future. I was too lazy to
actually set up anything spectacular (even though I was working as a web developer during this time).
The domain was pointed towards an <a href="https://about.me">about.me</a> page, which was the simplest solution at the time.
It allowed me to say a few words about myself, and host a CV in the form of a PDF.</p>
<p>However, gradually I've become more interested in actually hosting a technical blog and started to look into possible options.
At work I was building mostly sites using WordPress which could have worked well at the time, but would required
a whole hosting solution (including support for PHP). I was aware of Github pages at the time, and given that there was no
need to update the Blog by non-technical people, I've decided to go down the route of a static site generator.</p>
<h2 id="go-hugo-go">Go Hugo go!</h2>
<p>Enter <a href="https://gohugo.io">Hugo</a>. While I hadn't written anything serious in Go at that time (and haven't since),
it was the (new?) cool kid on the block and how could I <strong>not</strong> give it try? Looking back, it was a bad fit from the beginning.
It's main selling point - The world’s fastest framework for building websites - is great if you're having a site big
enough to run into this problem (I definitely didn't).</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Hugo <br>
The world’s fastest framework for building websites</p>
<p><cite><a href="https://gohugo.io">gohugo.io</a></cite></p>
</blockquote>
<p>There are many <a href="https://themes.gohugo.io">existing themes</a> for Hugo, but being a web developer at that time,
I obviously wanted to write my own. My unfamiliarity of <a href="https://pkg.go.dev/text/template">Go templates</a>,
as well as Hugo's complex <a href="https://gohugo.io/templates/lookup-order/">template hierarchy</a> made this a frustrating experience.
Don't get me wrong, I still think Hugo is a great tool if you're running a static site at scale (and maybe if you're
a Go developer).</p>
<p>I made it work in the end and was able to publish a static page to Github. But I was never fully happy with the result.
If memory serves right, it was shortly after that I found a new job, moved to a different country and never found the time
nor motivation to continue working or publishing to the blog.</p>
<h2 id="static-site-generation-as-a-library">Static site generation as a library</h2>
<p>Fast forward a few years. When 2020 Covid pandemic started, I suddenly had more time on my hand.
Stuck at home, I've started to rekindle with the idea of having a blog. At the same time I've learned about
the <a href="https://jaspervdj.be/hakyll/">Hakyll</a> project. While the name is a homage to the famous <a href="https://jekyllrb.com">Jekyll</a>
generator, it utilizes a completely different approach to static site generation.</p>
<p>Most static site generators (SSG) have a predefined set of features which are controlled via a configuration file.
Hakyll on the contrary is a library of different functions and modules, which let you write your own static site generator.
This sounds complicated at first, but in most cases is rather simple (check out some of their
<a href="https://jaspervdj.be/hakyll/tutorials/03-rules-routes-compilers.html">examples</a>).
The main benefit of this approach is that it allows you to easily customize your build process and
add features to your site, which are not yet present in other, pre-defined SSGs.</p>
<p>While I liked the idea of constructing the build of my site as a composition of different library components,
Hakyll is written in Haskell, which I'm not too familiar with.
My attempts to build <a href="https://github.com/MoritzHamann/fss">something similar</a> in <code>F#</code> did unfortunately not turn out to
be successful (yet :)). Once the lockdown was lifted, I moved into a new role at work and - yet again -
forgot about the idea of reviving my blog.</p>
<h2 id="starting-from-scratch-using-metalsmith">Starting from scratch using metalsmith</h2>
<p>Over the last few weekends, I sat down and started from scratch. In order to customize the build process, I've used the minimal, but extendable <a href="https://metalsmith.io">Metalsmith</a>
library. It has a similar approach to Hakyll but is written in JavaScript, which I'm more familiar with, given my day-to-day work.
While there were a few hick ups here and there - which I'll write in the future in more detail about - it was mostly smooth sailing.
The biggest issue at the moment is a somewhat broken live reload in the browser, which works <em>most</em> of the time.</p>
]]></description><link>http://moritzhamann.com/blog/2023-06-28-new-site.html</link><guid isPermaLink="true">http://moritzhamann.com/blog/2023-06-28-new-site.html</guid><pubDate>Wed, 28 Jun 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Handling datetime entries with native HTML inputs]]></title><description><![CDATA[<p>Recently I needed to handle datetime objects in a small web application. In the past I've reached out for some
JavaScript polyfill library to have a visual input widget for the user. But trying to keep the dependencies small this
time, I've checked what new input types HTML 5 has to offer and how well they are supported out of the box.</p>
<p>While the current support is surprisingly good, you may still want to fall back to a JavaScript alternative, especially
when support on iOS mobile is required. Following is a summary of the experience (in 2024) for different HTML input
types related to date and time.</p>
<h2 id="first-candidate-datetime-local">First candidate: "datetime-local"</h2>
<p>The most obvious first choice would be <code>&lt;input type="datetime-local"&gt;</code> which promises to handle date and time in a
single input field. Both <a href="https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/Web/HTML/Element/input/datetime-local">MDN</a> and the
actual <a href="https://html.spec.whatwg.org/multipage/input.html#local-date-and-time-state-(type=datetime-local)">W3C
specification</a> give a
very detailed description of the input field, including its supported attributes. For the sake of this article, I'm not
gonna repeat all of it here.</p>
<p>To get a first impression how the input field looks and behave, here is an example with default values:</p>
<figure><label>Example input: </label><input type="datetime-local"></figure>

<p>On all major desktop browsers tested (Safari, Firefox, Chrome on MacOS) the UX of the keyboard input is actually quite
good, i.e. using <code>&lt;tab&gt;</code> will jump through the input mask as you would expect, and the order of year, month and day
corresponds to my local setting. All three browser provide a "calender" popup, which varies in quality. Firefox and
Safari only allow to set the date, while Chrome provides input for time as well. Chrome and Firefox provide a
"hierarchical" date selection, i.e. the user can step out of the current month to select the year and month directly,
which can be very useful when selecting dates which are years in the past (Safari requires the user to step back one
month at a time).</p>
<p>Interestingly on mobile, the keyboard input is <em>skipped completely</em> and focusing the input field will directly open a
native widget for date and time.</p>
<p>So far so good. The "datetime-local" input field seems to handle the use case quite well. However, by default the field
only allows the user to input or edit time values for hours and minutes (not seconds). Consulting MDN again, the reason
for this behaviour is the default value of its <code>step</code> attribute. Quoting MDN</p>
<blockquote>
<p>[...] The step attribute is a number that specifies the granularity that the value must adhere to, or the special
value any, which is described below. Only values which are equal to the basis for stepping (min if specified, value
otherwise, and an appropriate default value if neither of those is provided) are valid. [...]</p>
<p>[...] For datetime-local inputs, the value of step is given in seconds, with a scaling factor of 1000 (since the
underlying numeric value is in milliseconds). The default value of step is 60, indicating 60 seconds (or 1 minute, or
60,000 milliseconds). [...]</p>
<p><em>- <a href="https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/Web/HTML/Element/input/datetime-local#step">MDN</a></em></p>
</blockquote>
<p>As mentioned, the default value for <code>step</code> is "60", i.e. full minute increments. I assume, this is the reason why all
browsers prevent the entry or modification of seconds by default. On a side note, this behaviour seems to be fully based
on an interpretation by browser vendors, since the <a href="https://html.spec.whatwg.org/multipage/input.html#local-date-and-time-state-(type=datetime-local)">HTML 5
specification</a>
mentions the <code>step</code> attribute only in the context of validation and does <em>not</em> link it to the presentation and UX
behaviour of the input field.</p>
<p>Setting <code>step="1"</code> should give us the ability to handle seconds as well. How well is this working in practice?</p>
<figure><label>Example input with <code>step="1"</code>: </label><input type="datetime-local" step="1"></figure>

<p>All <em>desktop</em> browser tested support the <code>step</code> attribute, and setting <code>step</code> to anything other than a multiply of 60
will allow the user to enter <em>arbitrary</em> values for seconds independent of the chosen step value. If a <a href="https://html.spec.whatwg.org/multipage/form-control-infrastructure.html#suffering-from-a-step-mismatch">step
mismatch</a>
occurs,  the input field is marked as invalid (including the <code>:invalid</code> pseudo CSS class) and form submission is
prevented. There is no dedicated UI widget which limits the entry to only valid step values (e.g. selecting only hours
in case <code>step="3600"</code>). </p>
<p>However it looks like the support for <em>mobile</em> browsers, is servery lacking. I.e. even after setting <code>step="1"</code>, mobile
browser will provide <strong>no way</strong> to input time values beyond hours and minutes. I've tested this with Chrome, Firefox and
Edge on Android, as well as Safari and Chrome on iOS. All of those browsers won't let the user enter numbers directly
but bring up the native datetime entry field, limited to hours and minutes. What makes this even worse (in my opinion)
is the fact that the <code>step</code> attribute is still honoured during form validation. On top of that, modifying a
pre-populated input field will <strong>zero out</strong> the seconds, with no way to reenter those values again.</p>
<p><strong>So in summary:</strong> using <code>&lt;input type="datetime-local"&gt;</code> works fine as long as</p>
<ul>
<li>the application only cares about hours and minutes</li>
<li>or if seconds are required, mobile support is not needed</li>
</ul>
<details>
<summary>More examples for different step values (including validation and serialization behaviour)</summary>

<form>
<dl>
    <dt>Default:</dt>
    <dd>
        <input type="datetime-local" id="default" name="default"><br>
        Serialization: <span id="outputDefault"></span>
    </dd>
    <dt><code>step="1"</code>:</dt>
    <dd>
        <input type="datetime-local" id="step1" name="step1" step="1"><br>
        Serialization: <span id="outputStep1"></span>
    </dd>
    <dt><code>step="3600"</code>:</dt>
    <dd>
        <input type="datetime-local" id="step3600" name="step3600" step="3600"><br>
        Serialization: <span id="outputStep3600"></span>
    </dd>
    <dt><code>step="25"</code>:</dt>
    <dd>
        <input type="datetime-local" id="step25" name="step25" step="25"><br>
        Serialization: <span id="outputStep25"></span>
    </dd>
    <dt><code>step="15" value="2024-02-02T14:27:20"</code> (step mismatch):</dt>
    <dd>
        <input type="datetime-local" id="prefilled" name="prefilled" step="15" value="2024-02-02T14:27:20"><br>
        Serialization: <span id="outputPrefilled"></span>
    </dd>
</dl>
<button type="submit">Validate</button>
</form>
<script>
    function el(idVal) {
        return document.getElementById(idVal);
    }
    function setup(input, out) {
        input.addEventListener("change", (ev) => out.textContent = input.value);
        out.textContent = input.value;
    }
    setup(el("default"), el("outputDefault"));
    setup(el("step1"), el("outputStep1"));
    setup(el("step3600"), el("outputStep3600"));
    setup(el("step25"), el("outputStep25"));
    setup(el("prefilled"), el("outputPrefilled"));
</script>
</details>


<h2 id="second-option-typedate-and-typetime">Second option: type="date" and type="time"</h2>
<p>In addition to <code>datetime-local</code>, the HTML spec provides the <code>date</code> and <code>time</code> input types (in addition to <code>month</code> and
<code>week</code>). Let's see if those inputs have better support on mobile browsers. If so, both could be combined to handle
datetimes. The downside is obviously a slightly different UX, since two different input fields need to be set (with
different popups) rather than one. Although depending on the scenario, this could also be seen as beneficial.</p>
<p>Similar to "datetime-local", both input types support the <code>step</code> attribute. In case of of "time", it reflects number of
seconds, for "date" it's the number of days. Setting the value to "1" gives us</p>
<figure>
<label>Date: </label><input type="date" step="1">
<label>Time: </label><input type="time" step="1">
</figure>

<p>Surprisingly, using <code>&lt;input type="time" step="1"&gt;</code> on Android with Edge, Chrome and Firefox gives us a popup which
supports the entry of seconds! It's interesting to see that the same input dialog was not used for "datetime-local". I
haven't done any mobile development, so I don't know if this is a fundamental limitations of the underlying OS dialog.
However, when used under iOS (Safari and Chrome) the popup is still limited to hours and minutes.</p>
<p><strong>In summary:</strong> Splitting the entry of a datetime into its date and time parts and using the corresponding input types,
works great except for the limitation that iOS still does not support a time resolution of seconds.</p>
<h2 id="other-things-to-keep-in-mind">Other things to keep in mind</h2>
<p>There are two other things I've stumbled upon when handling the form values of <code>datetime-local</code> and
<code>time</code> on the backend.</p>
<ol>
<li>The serialization format of both fields can depend on their current value. While the base format is
<code>YYYY-mm-ddTHH:MM:SS</code> (or <code>HH:MM:SS</code> for "time"), the specification states that the seconds <em>can</em> be dropped in case
seconds are zero. For all browser I've tested this is true, so 24th of Dec. 2024, 10:24:<strong>00</strong> will serialize to
<code>2024-12-24T10:24</code>. Hence, the backend validation and parsing logic will need to be able to handle the different
formats.</li>
<li>By design none of the entry field will provide timezone information, not even the current offset of the local
environment. <a href="https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/Web/HTML/Element/input/datetime-local#setting_timezones">MDN
suggests</a> to either
have a dropdown field with all possible offsets (which is just a horrible UX, given that the correct one can not be
preselected) or - if the current user is logged in and has a default timezone set in the account - use a hidden input
field with the offset.</li>
</ol>
<p>Not the end of the world, but definitely a small annoyance which broke my form handling at the beginning.</p>
<h2 id="why-it-matters">Why it matters</h2>
<p>I'm personally happy to see the support of date and time values in HTML forms improving. It provides a better unified UX
experience throughout the web, is great for quick prototyping as well as internal tools and can reduce the download and
execution overhead of web applications. Obviously, third party solution still have their place, especially if data entry
is one of the key parts of the application.</p>
<p>There is however an argument to be made about the ever growing complexity of the web standard, which makes implementing
new browser engines more and more difficult. But I guess this is a discussion for another time.</p>
]]></description><link>http://moritzhamann.com/blog/2024-09-15-handling-datetime-entries-native-html.html</link><guid isPermaLink="true">http://moritzhamann.com/blog/2024-09-15-handling-datetime-entries-native-html.html</guid><pubDate>Sun, 15 Sep 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Switching to 5Ghz wifi made the Raspberry Pi fly again]]></title><description><![CDATA[<p>For the last few months my Raspberry Pi 4 was happily running on my desk, tucked away next to the monitor. It's serving
a small web app in golang on the internal network and tailscale. I've never noticed any latency problems with it, so it
took me by surprise when I deployed some OCaml experiments on the Pi and observed a lot of HTTP connection timeouts and
name resolution errors while fetching some URLs concurrently.</p>
<p>Since I cross compiled the experiment from my M1, I first thought there might by some issues related to the TLS setup in
Cohttp. So I've copied the source files over ssh and installed all dependencies via opam. Average download speed of
<em>0.5 Mbit/s</em>. WTF? Some unrelated <code>git clone</code> showed the same speed and just timed out...</p>
<p>Running <code>uptime</code> showed 120 days, so I blamed it on some obscure wifi stack issue and did what most people would:</p>
<figure>
    <iframe src="https://giphy.com/embed/DUtVdGeIU8lmo" width="480" height="264" style="" frameborder="0" class="giphy-embed" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>
</figure>

<p>It did not disappoint: download speed was back to <em>80 Mbit/s</em> and no connection errors while fetching the URLs. Problem solved.</p>
<p>Or so I thought. The next day the same thing happened again. How is this possible? While searching the Raspberry pi
forum two things caught my eye: <a href="https://forums.raspberrypi.com/viewtopic.php?t=320076">USB3 is interfering with 2.4Ghz wifi</a>
and <a href="https://forums.raspberrypi.com/viewtopic.php?t=305861">extremly slow wifi on pi4</a>. Both reported slow wifi speeds
on 2.4Ghz, which went away after switching to 5Ghz.</p>
<p>And then it dawned on me. I'm running our network on both frequencies under the same name. The day before, when I
rebooted the Pi the wifi did not connect automatically, so I temporarily plugged the Pi into my monitor and selected the
wifi via the GUI. Which showed 5GHz in the tooltip. Could this have changed? Using <code>nmcli</code> the current network was
indeed listed as 2.4Ghz.</p>
<pre><code>$ nmcli -f IN-USE,SSID,BSSID,FREQ device wifi list
IN-USE  SSID       BSSID              FREQ
*       xxxxxxxxx  yy:yy:yy:yy:yy:yy  2412 MHz
        xxxxxxxxx  zz:zz:zz:zz:zz:zz  5200 MHz
</code></pre>
<p>Changing the network via</p>
<pre><code>$ sudo nmcli device wifi connect zz:zz:zz:zz:zz:zz password &lt;pw&gt;
</code></pre>
<p>had the desired effect and the download speed is back to normal. We can make this permanent by adding <code>band=a</code> in the
<code>[wifi]</code> section of <code>/etc/NetworkManager/system-connections/preconfigured.nmconnection</code> and/or <code>&lt;SSID&gt;.nmconnection</code> in
the same folder.</p>
<p>I still not sure what exactly the issue with the 2.4GHz network is, especially given that this didn't seem to have
happened in the past. Potentially some interference due to the ceiling between the Pi and the router, the fancy metal
enclosure I got or a smaller wifi antenna in the Pi. But it doesn't really matter, since it's been working fine for the
last few days, and once the brand new network cable arrives, the Pi will be plugged directly into the router.</p>
<figure>
    <iframe src="https://giphy.com/embed/BPJmthQ3YRwD6QqcVD" width="480" height="269" style="" frameborder="0" class="giphy-embed" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>
</figure>
]]></description><link>http://moritzhamann.com/blog/2024-10-08-raspberrypi-wifi-freq.html</link><guid isPermaLink="true">http://moritzhamann.com/blog/2024-10-08-raspberrypi-wifi-freq.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 08 Oct 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Neovim: Logging utilities]]></title><description><![CDATA[<p>When writing a Neovim configuration or plugin, it sometimes can become annoying when trying to debug an issue. The
available debug utilities are either <code>print()</code> or <code>vim.notify()</code>. In both cases (by default <code>vim.notify()</code> is the same
as <code>print()</code>), the log messes are written to <code>:messages</code>, which does not allow to further select or process the printed
text (as far as I'm aware).</p>
<h2 id="setup">Setup</h2>
<p>However, thanks to the flexibility of Neovim we can write our own logging function, which writes the output to a
temporary logging buffer. A rough outline of such a function could be</p>
<pre><code class="language-lua">--- @class LogOptions
--- @field namespace string namespace the log belongs to


local M = {}

--- @param msg string|table&lt;string&gt; log message (either single line or array
---                                 of lines to accept vim.inspect() output)
--- @param level integer|nil log level defined in vim.log.levels
--- @param options LogOptions allows us to set different logging namespaces
M.log = function(msg, level, options)

    -- extracting a namespace to determine which buffer to log to
    local opts = options or {}
    local ns = opts.namespace or "default"

    -- find the corresponding buffer and if there is no such buffer, create one
    local buffer_name = M.buffer_name(ns)
    local buffer = M.find_log_buffer(buffer_name)
    if buffer == nil then
        buffer = vim.api.nvim_create_buf(true, true)
        vim.api.nvim_buf_set_name(buffer, buffer_name)
    end

    -- transform the integer log level to its string representation.
    local level_str = "INFO"
    for l, i in pairs(vim.log.levels) do
        if level == i  then
            level_str = l
        end
    end


    -- ensure `msg` is always a table to make processing simpler
    if type(msg) == "string" then
        msg = {msg}
    end

    -- Split `msg` on newlines, since nvim_buf_set_lines() does not like them
    msg = vim.tbl_map(function(line)
        return vim.split(line, "\n")
    end, msg)
    msg = vim.iter(msg):flatten(1):totable()

    -- for each line add the log level
    local complete_msg = vim.tbl_map(function (line)
        return "[" .. level_str .. "] " .. line
    end, msg)

    -- actually add the lines to the buffer
    vim.api.nvim_buf_set_lines(buffer, -1, -1, true, complete_msg)
end


--- @param namespace string
M.buffer_name = function (namespace)
    return "LOG-" .. namespace
end


--- @param buffer_name string
M.find_log_buffer = function(buffer_name)
    local buffer_list = vim.api.nvim_list_bufs()
    for _, buf_num in ipairs(buffer_list) do
        local name = vim.fn.bufname(buf_num)
        if name == buffer_name then
            return buf_num
        end
    end
    return nil
end


--- @param namespace string
M.create_logger = function(namespace)
    local opts = {namespace = namespace}
    local logging_func_for = function(level)
        return function(msg)
            M.log(msg, level, opts)
        end
    end

    return {
        trace = logging_func_for(vim.log.levels.TRACE),
        debug = logging_func_for(vim.log.levels.DEBUG),
        info = logging_func_for(vim.log.levels.INFO),
        warn = logging_func_for(vim.log.levels.WARN),
        error = logging_func_for(vim.log.levels.ERROR),
    }
end
</code></pre>
<p>This can directly be tested via</p>
<pre><code>:lua require("myFileName").log("Some log message", vim.log.levels.INFO, {namespace="myNameSpace"})
</code></pre>
<p>which should create a new buffer called <code>LOG-myNameSpace</code> with the content <code>[INFO] Some log message</code>.</p>
<p>The above is just a rough idea, and could be customized further. I.e. rather than having different buffers per
namespace, it could log to a single one and prefix the messages with the namespace. Or use <code>print()</code> if a namespace is
not set. You get the idea.</p>
<h2 id="how-to-use">How to use</h2>
<p>There are two ways on how to use this:</p>
<ol>
<li>use the log function directly in our plugin</li>
<li>or replace the existing <code>vim.notify()</code> function with our logging function.</li>
</ol>
<p>The first option is straight forward and ensures that no other plugin will use the custom logging function:</p>
<pre><code class="language-lua">    -- create a namespaced logger
    local log = require("myFileName").create_logger("myNameSpace")

    -- use it
    log.info("Hello World")
    log.error("That's not right")
    log.debug(vim.inspect(vim.lsp.buf))

    -- content of the corresponding LOG-myNameSpace buffer
    -- [INFO] Hello World
    -- [ERROR] That's not right
    -- [DEBUG] {
    -- [DEBUG]   add_workspace_folder = &lt;function 1&gt;,
    -- [DEBUG]   clear_references = &lt;function 2&gt;,
    -- [DEBUG]   code_action = &lt;function 3&gt;,
    -- [DEBUG]   completion = &lt;function 4&gt;,
    -- [DEBUG]   declaration = &lt;function 5&gt;,
    -- [DEBUG]   definition = &lt;function 6&gt;,
    -- [DEBUG]   document_highlight = &lt;function 7&gt;,
    -- [DEBUG]   document_symbol = &lt;function 8&gt;,
    -- [DEBUG]   execute_command = &lt;function 9&gt;,
    -- [DEBUG]   format = &lt;function 10&gt;,
    -- [DEBUG]   hover = &lt;function 11&gt;,
    -- [DEBUG]   implementation = &lt;function 12&gt;,
    -- [DEBUG]   incoming_calls = &lt;function 13&gt;,
    -- [DEBUG]   list_workspace_folders = &lt;function 14&gt;,
    -- [DEBUG]   outgoing_calls = &lt;function 15&gt;,
    -- [DEBUG]   references = &lt;function 16&gt;,
    -- [DEBUG]   remove_workspace_folder = &lt;function 17&gt;,
    -- [DEBUG]   rename = &lt;function 18&gt;,
    -- [DEBUG]   signature_help = &lt;function 19&gt;,
    -- [DEBUG]   type_definition = &lt;function 20&gt;,
    -- [DEBUG]   typehierarchy = &lt;function 21&gt;,
    -- [DEBUG]   workspace_symbol = &lt;function 22&gt;
    -- [DEBUG] }
</code></pre>
<p>The second option can be done by assigning the log function</p>
<pre><code>vim.notify = require("myFileName").log
</code></pre>
<p>somewhere during the initialization of your lua dotfiles. It has the interesting side effect that other plugins using
<code>vim.notify()</code> now also log into the temporary buffer.</p>
]]></description><link>http://moritzhamann.com/blog/2024-10-27-logging-in-neovim.html</link><guid isPermaLink="true">http://moritzhamann.com/blog/2024-10-27-logging-in-neovim.html</guid><pubDate>Sun, 27 Oct 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Neovim: Tips and tricks for OCaml's LSP server]]></title><description><![CDATA[<p>When developing OCaml projects in Neovim, the OCaml language server (<a href="https://github.com/ocaml/ocaml-lsp">ocamllsp</a>) can
be of great help. It should just work out of the box, however there are few tweaks you can do in order to
improve your developer experience even more.</p>
<h2 id="first-things-first-setting-everything-up">First things first: Setting everything up</h2>
<p>I'm assuming you have a working OCaml and opam environment. If not, follow the steps on the official <a href="https://ocaml.org/install">"Getting
Started"</a> page first.</p>
<p>After that, let's make sure all the necessary packages are installed:</p>
<pre><code>$ opam install ocaml-lsp-server ocamlformat dune
</code></pre>
<p>This will install the following packages globally</p>
<ul>
<li><code>ocaml-lsp-server</code>: the language server itself (the executable is called <code>ocamllsp</code>)</li>
<li><code>ocamlformat</code>: the file formatting tool which ocamllsp uses</li>
<li><code>dune</code>: the newest OCaml build system.</li>
</ul>
<p>In order to simplify the server configuration, we're using <a href="https://github.com/neovim/nvim-lspconfig">nvim-lspconfig</a>.
Make sure to follow your package manager's instructions on how to add lspconfig to your Neovim installation. Once this is
done, add a basic configuration for <code>ocamllsp</code> somewhere in your Lua config files:</p>
<pre><code class="language-lua">local lsp_config = require('lspconfig')
lsp_config['ocamllsp'].setup({})
</code></pre>
<p>Once you've reloaded your configuration, you should have a working LSP integration while editing OCaml source files.</p>
<details>
<summary>Bonus: LSP keybindings</summary>

<p>Last but not least, if you have not configured your LSP keybindings so far, feel free to use those as your inspiration:</p>
<pre><code class="language-lua">vim.api.nvim_create_autocmd('LspAttach', {
    group = vim.api.nvim_create_augroup('UserLspConfig', {}),
    callback = function(event)
        local opts = { buffer = event.buf }
        vim.keymap.set('n', 'gD', vim.lsp.buf.declaration, opts)
        vim.keymap.set('n', 'gd', vim.lsp.buf.definition, opts)
        vim.keymap.set('n', 'gt', vim.lsp.buf.type_definition, opts)
        vim.keymap.set('n', 'K', vim.lsp.buf.hover, opts)
        vim.keymap.set('n', 'gi', vim.lsp.buf.implementation, opts)
        vim.keymap.set('n', '&lt;C-k&gt;', vim.lsp.buf.signature_help, opts)
        vim.keymap.set('n', '&lt;leader&gt;wa', vim.lsp.buf.add_workspace_folder, opts)
        vim.keymap.set('n', '&lt;leader&gt;wr', vim.lsp.buf.remove_workspace_folder, opts)
        vim.keymap.set('n', '&lt;leader&gt;wl', function()
            print(vim.inspect(vim.lsp.buf.list_workspace_folders()))
        end, opts)
        vim.keymap.set('n', '&lt;leader&gt;H', vim.lsp.buf.typehierarchy, opts)
        vim.keymap.set('n', '&lt;leader&gt;rn', vim.lsp.buf.rename, opts)
        vim.keymap.set({ 'n', 'v' }, '&lt;leader&gt;ca', vim.lsp.buf.code_action, opts)
        vim.keymap.set('n', 'gr', vim.lsp.buf.references, opts)
        vim.keymap.set('n', '&lt;leader&gt;fo', function()
            vim.lsp.buf.format { async = true }
        end, opts)
    end,
})
</code></pre>
</details>

<h2 id="dune-rpc-keeping-lsp-information-up-to-date">Dune RPC: keeping LSP information up to date</h2>
<p>Once you started using the LSP server, you may notice that from time to time diagnostic information are not up to
date. This often happens when new files or modules are added the project. One way to solve those issues is to build the
project with <code>dune build</code> followed by <code>:LspRestart</code> in Neovim. This will ensure that the latest build
information are available to ocamllsp.</p>
<p>However, there is a much better way by utilizing the <a href="https://dune.readthedocs.io/en/latest/rpc.html">RPC mechanism</a> of
dune. Newer versions of <code>dune</code> will start an (experimental) RPC server when a "watch" build is started. ocamllsp can
utilize this RPC mechanism to get notifications about new build information and update the editor diagnostics
accordingly.</p>
<p>There is configuration for ocamllsp needed, since it should recognize the running <code>dune</code> process and automatically
establish the RPC connection. The only thing to do is to start a continuous build of your project via the <code>-w</code> flag
before the LSP server is started (e.g. <code>dune build -w</code> or <code>dune exec -w</code>).</p>
<h2 id="running-dune-in-a-separate-build-directory">Running Dune in a separate build directory</h2>
<blockquote>
<p><strong>Correction:</strong>
A previous version of this article stated that ocamllsp will work out of the box if the continuous dune build is
running in a different build folder. This is not correct, as it needs additional configuration as stated below.</p>
<p>See also <a href="https://github.com/ocaml/ocaml-lsp/issues/1433">this GitHub issue</a> for more information.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>While the continuous dune build gives up-to-date diagnostics of the project, there is one annoying downside - it will
lock your build directory for other dune processes. I.e. you won't be able to execute <code>dune exec</code> or <code>dune runtest</code>
while the build process is running. You could obviously stop the build, run your other commands and then restart the
build, but this gets annoying fast.</p>
<p>Another way is to use different build directories - one for your continuous <code>dune</code> builds which provide realtime
diagnostics to ocamllsp - and the default directory to execute tests and programs. Dune supports this via the
<code>--build-dir=&lt;path&gt;</code> option. E.g. to execute the dune instance for ocamllsp in the <code>_build_lsp</code> folder, run</p>
<pre><code>$ dune build -w --build-dir=_build_lsp
</code></pre>
<p>In order for ocamllsp to recognize non-standard build directories, the <code>DUNE_BUILD_DIR</code> environment variable needs to be
set accordingly. In lspconfig, this can be achieved by adding the <code>cmd_env</code> config parameter to the ocamllsp entry</p>
<pre><code class="language-lua">lsp_config['ocamllsp'].setup({
    cmd_env = {DUNE_BUILD_DIR = '_build_lsp'},
    --- ...
})
</code></pre>
<p>This will ensure that one Dune instance is running builds in <code>_build_lsp</code> and provides up to date diagnostics to
<code>ocamllsp</code> via RPC, while you can still execute tests and run your OCaml programs simultaneously in the default build
directory.</p>
<h2 id="help-my-files-are-not-formatting">Help! My files are not formatting</h2>
<p>If the LSP format command is not doing anything, the most likely  reason is a missing <code>.ocamlformat</code> file. Without it,
the <code>ocamlformat</code> tool will <strong>not</strong> change any files. To solve the issue, simply add a <code>.ocamlformat</code> file at the root
of your project (even an empty one should do). For more details on the formatting options available via this file, run
<code>man ocamlformat</code> or check the <a href="https://ocaml.org/p/ocamlformat/0.26.2/doc/index.html">online documentation</a>.</p>
]]></description><link>http://moritzhamann.com/blog/2024-12-18-ocamllsp-in-neovim.html</link><guid isPermaLink="true">http://moritzhamann.com/blog/2024-12-18-ocamllsp-in-neovim.html</guid><pubDate>Wed, 18 Dec 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>